LAURENCE SMITH

An experienced team leader with a track record of using advanced analytical techniques to deliver innovative solutions to business problems. I successfully understand the challenges presented, translate them into mathematical problems, use my team and my expertise to solve them and then present back in a way that non-technical senior stakeholders understand and have confidence in. I care deeply about my team and coach them to take ownership of, and deliver, the team vision.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

Degree: Mathematics, Oxford University, First Class Honours (1999)

A Levels: Further Maths - A, Maths - A, Economics - A, Geography - A (1996)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Commercial Credit Risk Modeller – Lloyds Banking Group Sep 2015 - current

- Managing and developing a team of modellers
- Lead the rebuild of the model for unquoted corporates giving a 10% uplift in power
- Recalibrating / updating models to comply with new regulations
- Working with internal stakeholders and the Prudential Regulation Authority to gain their trust and achieve approval
- Showed an ability to deliver through diligent planning and dedicated work
- Received a division level award for generating the idea of using robotics to re-rate credit portfolios and managing its development and delivery. Saved over 5,000 hours of time for Credit and ensured customers had more accurate risk ratings.

Pricing Modelling and Strategy Lead – Lloyds Banking Group Oct 2014 – Sep 2015

- Developed a vision for the team and achieved stakeholder buy-in
- Guided development of new pricing capabilities for mortgages, loans, savings and annuities through generating ideas and being a subject matter expert
- Upskilled the team's capabilities and lead the department's shift to a SAS Server
- Created and implemented a new governance process for the team to ensure outputs are of the highest quality

Senior Pricing Manager – Lloyds Banking Group

Jan 2012 - Sep 2014

- Lead a central pricing team using statistical and financial analysis of customer, competitor, and economic data to help optimise pricing decisions
- Generated value through developing new models and processes and embedding them in the product pricing teams:
 - Put the team on track to generate £300m in incremental income by 2017
 - Enhanced loans price optimisation with 20% uplift in profitability
- Convinced mortgages and annuities teams to invest in the analytical and pricing modelling skills of my team
- Worked closely with Data, Product and Governance teams to ensure my team delivered what was needed
- Managed:
 - A team of 15 people made up of contractors and permanent employees
 - People at a distance team was split over four locations
 - Recruitment grew team from 6 people when I was appointed
- Presented to over 250 people at the department end of year conference

Pricing Manager – Lloyds Banking Group

Jan 2010 - Dec 2011

Led mortgage retention pricing modelling:

Laurence Smith Page 1 of 2

- Built price sensitivity, propensity and NPV models and combined them to generate optimised individual prices for mortgage customers
- o Gained business agreement for the models to be used in live pricing
- Generated a 57% uplift in NPV for customers reaching the end of a deal
- Developed good relationships with stakeholders

Profitability Analysis Manager – Lloyds Banking Group

Oct 2007 - Dec 2009

- Developed and launched models to enhance profitability of loans' mailings, generating incremental NPV of £1m a year
- Determined the need for, designed and built Loan Remaining Value NPV model and promoted it to my department. Teams used it to: develop a customer retention strategy, measure the value of marketing and optimise marketing spend.
- Calculated NPVs for home insurance and motor insurance

Direct Pricing Manager - Aviva

Mar 2006 - Sep 2007

- Led the pricing for the development and successful launch of a new aggregator car insurance product, enabling brand differentiation:
 - Developed a new pricing algorithm
 - Worked with Statistical Risk Team, Actuarial department, Underwriting, Marketing, Propositions and Finance
 - Negotiated profit / sales trade off with other departments and third party suppliers
- Priced Norwich Union's breakdown cover
- Led the planning process for the Pricing Team: forecasting premiums, conversion rates and retention rates
- Improved pricing algorithms through analysing the effects of our and our competitors' price changes and enhancing price sensitivity measurement

Consultant – Self Employed Consultant – Volterra Consulting Ltd

2004 - 2005

1999 - 2004

- Developed new analytical techniques to solve business and public sector problems
- Generated new business, managed delivery and clients expectations, kept confidentialities, spoke at conferences and networked, wrote articles for the press
- Modelled the effect of social networks on the uptake of consumer goods and services. Used to understand and predict new product penetration and the effects of targeted advertising.
- Designed and created a model to assess the impact of potential incentives for companies to sign up to an emissions trading scheme. Adapted the model to provide results for the Department of the Environment
- Used fuzzy clustering analysis to identify key comparator and competitor cities for Glasgow, to assist in policy priorities and marketing
- Analysed predictability of crime figures and produced non-linear modelling of trends in crime

OTHER INFORMATION

Software: Recently: SAS, SQL, Python (beginner), Excel, PowerPoint, Word

Previously: R, VBA, MS Access, MS Project, HTML, Java, C, Visio, Visual

Basic

Social: I keep fit through Korean karate, running, cycling and chasing after my three

children

I enjoy keeping up to date with business, technology and data science news To relax I practise yoga, try to juggle and read fiction and business books

Laurence Smith Page 2 of 2